Finding Aid for Middle English Dictionary records, 1925-2008
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
For a while in the 1960s and 1970s, there was renewed interest in the University of Michigan's Early Modern English materials, which had been put aside indefinitely in 1939. R.C. Alston of Leeds University proposed to make use of the Michigan materials to prepare a dictionary of Tudor English (1475-1640), but faculty members in the Department of English concluded that the University was not prepared at that time to embark on a project as large as this. But local interest in such a project resumed, and Richard W. Bailey wrote a report in 1968 laying out the research that would need to be done for it. Thanks to a grant from the NEH in the early 1970s, Bailey, James Downer, and Jay L. Robinson were able to produce Early Modern English Materials (1975), a print handbook and bibliography with a microfiche index to a million words from the EMED files. For some years after 1975 it was hoped that work on a full-fledged dictionary could continue after the MED was completed, but that hope was abandoned and in 1994 the materials sent to the Oxford University Press for use in the third edition (in progress) of the OED.
Lewis era (1982-2001)
During 1982-1983 Robert E. Lewis worked with Kuhn during Kuhn's last year on the University of Michigan faculty, becoming editor-in-chief on Kuhn's retirement in 1983. During Lewis's editorship, as during Kurath's and Kuhn's, the reading program, which began under Moore in the 1930s, was continued, as editions of unpublished Middle English texts began to appear with ever-increasing frequency after World War II (and especially from the 1970s onward) and many previously edited texts began to be reedited. These were read by the staff, as they came to their attention and as time allowed, and quotations extracted from them for use in the words still to be edited.
Between 1982 and 1996, with a staff that again fluctuated between seven and thirteen editors (mostly full time), the editing continued to proceed at the faster rate, despite the fact that the amount of data was increasing, through the continuing extraction of quotations from newly edited texts. In 1996, as the editing was nearing its end, the number of editors had to be reduced, and, finally, in late 1997, approximately fifty years after it began according to Kurath's plan, the editing was completed by the three editors who were chosen to remain.
In 1982 the NEH awarded the project its second grant (with four additional ones to come between 1985 and 1994), in both outright and matching funds, and in 1985 and again in 1988 the Mellon Foundation made two additional large awards. From then to the end of 1996 the editing was supported jointly by the Mellon Foundation and the National Endowment. In 1993, however, when application was made to the NEH for the one last editing grant it needed, the matching funds from the Mellon Foundation were nearly exhausted, and the project undertook a three-year fund-raising campaign in North America to raise replacement funds. Thanks to an initial gift (and subsequent gifts) from A. Richard Diebold, Jr., and to contributions from well over two hundred individuals and institutions, the project was able to meet its matching-fund requirement, with enough left over to assist in completing the last stages of the editing in 1996-1997. Continued funding from the University of Michigan, primarily through the Office of the Vice President for Research, supported the other parts of the project to its conclusion in 2001.
In early 1984, after exploring various word-processing and printing systems during the previous year and a half, the project replaced its typewriter-generated production system in use since 1952 with a computer-assisted system, which allowed the MED, beginning with the Q-fascicle and Plan and Bibliography Supplement I, to update and revise its fonts and to increase its rate of publication to an average of three fascicles per year between Q and the final X-Y-Z fascicle in 2001. (The increased rate of publication can be attributed partly to an increase in the amount of reviewed copy, thanks to the use of one or more reviewers in addition to the editor-in-chief from 1983 on, and partly to a strict timetable for completing the final stages of the project between 1996 and 2001.) From Q through S the format of the earlier typewriter-generated pages was kept, but with the first T-fascicle, thanks to a customized package of Times Roman softfonts, some formatting changes were incorporated to increase readability (the most important of which were boldfaced dates and italicized short titles for the Middle English texts), and these changes continued through the rest of the alphabet.
With the publication of the final X-Y-Z fascicle in the summer of 2001, the completed MED proper runs to 14,939 pages in 115 fascicles (combined into thirteen volumes), with 54,081 separate entries and 891,531 quotations. The final figure of 14,939 pages is nearly double the 8,000 that Kurath had projected. That is partly because the definitions became more elaborate and more detailed as the MED progressed, but primarily because the number of illustrative quotations increased, though this was partly by default: there was simply more data added to the files (especially from the fifteenth century) as the editors proceeded through the alphabet.
Post-2001 era
In 2007 the final piece of the MED, the Plan and Bibliography, Second Edition, was published. This new edition contains a complete reshaping and rewriting by Lewis of Kurath's original Plan, with an up-to-date history of the project and a comprehensive guide to the entries and their constituent parts, and a revised Bibliography by Lewis and Mary Jane Williams, with the assistance of Marilyn S. Miller, of the texts used in the print dictionary, which amounts to over 7100 full entries, nearly half again as many as in the original 1954 bibliography and the 1984 supplemental bibliography combined, with notes on the changes in date, title, manuscript, or edition that took place in the print dictionary between 1952 and 2001.
Since 1998, thanks to a separate grant from the NEH in the previous year and with support from various units at the University of Michigan, an electronic version of the MED, under the direction of Frances McSparran of the Department of English and John Wilkin of the University Library, has been available to subscribers online; it constitutes one of the three resources in the Middle English Compendium (the other two are the HyperBibliography of Middle English, based on the MED bibliographies, and the Corpus of Middle English Prose and Verse, a series of fully searchable electronic texts linked to the HyperBibliography). The letters A through P of the print MED were keyboarded and then converted to SGML markup, the electronic files of Q through T were also converted to SGML markup, and the MED production staff themselves encoded U through Z in SGML, with the result that all of the existing print MED was made available online by the end of 2001.
From the early years of publication a print supplement was part of the long-range plan. The files for it began to be organized during Kuhn's editorship, and between then and 2001 they were systematically added to, with the result that by 2001 there were eighteen boxes of alphabetized supplementary materials. Public references to a supplement began to appear by 1961, and in the printed fascicles from R through Z cross-references were inserted to "Suppl." entries.
The kind of supplement envisioned originally was a short one, in which the obvious errors would be corrected, definitions and etymologies revised that were known to need revision, and the new words in the MED files added, much like the supplement to the Scottish National Dictionary (1976). But as work continued through the remainder of the alphabet, it became increasingly clear that, in view of the length of time that had elapsed since the first fascicle appeared (1952) and the changes in editorial practice that had taken place since then, the kind of supplement that would best serve the scholarly community would be a full and systematic one, which, in conjunction with the completed MED, would provide a coherent whole in which all entries would be similar in treatment, fullness, and coverage from A to Z.
The cost of producing this fuller kind of supplement, or even the shorter version, was beyond the University's means at the time, but some preliminary work was done during the summer of 2001, after the final fascicle had been sent to the printer, through a grant from the Office of the Vice President for Research awarded to Frances McSparran, when four members of the MED Production Staff organized and classified the supplementary materials, partially entered the additional quotations into the computer, and proofed them against the texts. Nothing further has been done on these materials since 2001 (except for some work by Lewis leading to an article on a Middle English prefix in 2005), but they are now available for consultation at the Bentley Library.
Chief Editors of the MED
1930-1934 Samuel Moore
1935-1945 Thomas A. Knott
1946-1961 Hans Kurath
1961-1983 Sherman M. Kuhn
1982-2001 Robert E. Lewis
In August of 2001 the administrative records and most of the materials pertaining to the history and making of the Middle English Dictionary (MED) from its beginnings at the University of Michigan in 1930 up to its completion in 2001 were deposited in the Bentley Historical Library by the project and by the administrative unit responsible for it, the Office of the Vice President for Research. These materials consist primarily of correspondence, administrative records (including budget), files on editorial matters, and miscellaneous files and notes on other matters. In February of 2010 the remainder of the MED materials was transferred to the Bentley Library from the Buhr Storage Facility, where they had been kept since the fall of 2001, along with the books from the former MED library (now dispersed), under the supervision of the Special Collections Library. All of these materials form a collection separate from the citation slips used in the printed MED (along with the supplementary slips), which are now catalogued as Middle English Dictionary Citation Slips. The total number of boxes in the present collection is 91 (of various sizes), amounting to 61 linear feet.
The Middle English Dictionary records are organized in three major subgroups, RECORDS BY EDITORIAL ERA, MISCELLANEOUS MED MATERIALS, and NON-MED MATERIALS.
In the first 20 boxes (21 linear feet) the materials are in standard-size boxes in 8 1/2" x 14" folders and are arranged strictly chronologically by the editorial eras of the chief editors: Samuel Moore (1930-1934), Thomas A. Knott (1935-1945), Hans Kurath (1946-1961), Sherman M. Kuhn (1961-1983), and Robert E. Lewis (1982-2001), except that the Moore and Knott eras have been combined because of the difficulty of separating the files, other than correspondence, in those two eras. In the later MED boxes (21 through 84), the materials are stored in a mixture of formats (8 1/2" x 14" folders, 6 1/2" x 9" cards, 3" x 5" cards and slips, etc.), the organization is topical, though still generally chronological. Non- MED materials (specifically, the Early Modern English Dictionary (EMED) materials) appear at the end (in boxes 79 through 91).
Subjects:
English language--Lexicography.; English language--Middle English, 1100-1500.; Knott, Thomas A. (Thomas Albert), 1880-1945.; Kuhn, Sherman M. (Sherman McAllister), 1907-1991.; Kurath, Hans, 1891-1992.; Lewis, Robert E.; Middle English dictionary.; Moore, Samuel 1877-1934.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Knott, Thomas A. (Thomas Albert), 1880-1945.; Kuhn, Sherman M. (Sherman McAllister), 1907-1991.; Kurath, Hans, 1891-1992.; Lewis, Robert E.; Middle English dictionary.; Moore, Samuel 1877-1934.; Slides.; Photographs.
Genre Terms:
Slides.; Photographs.
- Records by Editorial Era
  The subgroup RECORDS BY EDITORIAL ERA is organized in series reflecting the tenures of each of the chief MED editors. The series are: Moore-Knott Era, 1930-1945, Kurath Era, 1945-1961, Kuhn Era, 1961-1983, and Lewis Era, 1982-2001 (and later). Each of the series includes subseries relating to content: correspondence, administration and history, editorial matters. Additional subseries pertain to specific matters under particular editors such as the reading program, bibliography, production matters, and non-MED matters.
  Effort was made to retain the arrangement and the order of the original materials insofar as that was possible, but inevitably for the sake of consistency from one editorial era to another we had to adapt the arrangement to the emphases in each era. Correspondence, alphabetically arranged, always appears as the first category for all eras. This includes the chief editor's MED and professional, scholarly, and academic correspondence (including intra-university correspondence), both to and from him, with notes on the main correspondents, the subjects of the letters, and who else besides the chief editor was involved in answering letters. Each correspondent's letters are arranged chronologically, from earliest to latest. The only exception to this arrangement is in the Moore and Knott correspondence, where some letters were pasted together for filing in reverse chronological order, as was the custom in the 1930s and 1940s, and these have been kept as they were originally, with the latest on top.
  The correspondence is always followed by administrative records and historical files, alphabetically arranged, which contain information on budget requests and staff salaries by year, the minutes of the various committees either overseeing or participating in the work of the MED (chiefly the Committee on Dictionaries from 1930 to 1977, the MED Council and various internal committees thereafter), reports (both annual and miscellaneous), external financial support and grant applications, hiring of editors, ordering of books for the MED library, equipment inventories, statements of account, and the like.
  Then follow files and records on editorial matters, also alphabetically arranged: these include such topics as bibliography, dialects, editing progress, editors' guides and style books, papers and articles on various subjects pertaining to the MED, and reviews after publishing began.
  Following these fixed categories appear, where appropriate according to the principal activities of each era, some separate categories: for example, for the reading program (which was an especially important activity in Moore's era, to a lesser extent in Knott's), for the bibliography (which was in the process of being established in Kurath's era), and for production matters (which were particularly extensive in the changeover from typewriters to computers in Lewis's era).
  Finally, for all but one of the editorial eras, there is a category called non- MED materials, which contains files on the EMED (these are particularly extensive during the Moore and Knott eras), correspondence other than that pertaining to the MED if it is extensive, research and editorial matters not directly related to work on the MED, and occasional files on graduate and undergraduate class matters and civic affairs.
  - Moore-Knott Era 1930-1945
    Moore and Knott eras (1930-1945). The correspondence from the Moore and Knott eras (1930-1934 and 1935-1945) is extensive (2.6 linear feet), reflecting the historical fact that the project was in its infancy at the University of Michigan and many decisions had to be made, not least those about financial matters at a time of severe economic depression and those having to do with the samples produced during the Knott era.
    - Moore-Era Correspondence 1930-1934
      Moore's correspondence was primarily with well known and influential Middle English scholars of the time, containing extensive exchanges between Moore and Albert C. Baugh (Pennsylvania; also a member of the Modern Language Association [MLA] Advisory Committee on the MED), Carleton Brown (MLA), W.F. Bryan (Northwestern), Thomas A. Knott (frequently about their joint publication, Elements of Old English), Percy Long (MLA), Lorenz Morsbach (G旦ttingen), Clark Northup (editor of the dictionary when it was housed at Cornell), Henry L. Savage (Princeton), Mary S. Serjeantson (London), James F. Willard (Colorado), R.M. Wilson (Leeds), and many of the volunteer readers of Middle English texts. In addition to Moore, C.C. Fries, Editor of the EMED, frequently answered letters, as did MED editors Sanford Meech and James Rettger and sometimes administrative staff members Helen Snyder and Eleanore Stuhlmann.
      - A (Box 1)
      - Allen, Hope Emily (mainly to and from Fries) (Box 1)
      - Ba-Bo (Box 1)
      - Br-Bu (Box 1)
      - Ca-Ch (Box 1)
      - Cl-Cu (Box 1)
      - D (Box 1)
      - E (Box 1)
      - F (Box 1)
      - G (Box 1)
      - H (Box 1)
      - I-J (Box 1)
      - K (Box 1)
      - La-Lock (Box 1)
      - Lon-Lu (Box 1)
      - Ma-Me (Box 1)
      - MED
        - Moore correspondence with MED staff while on sabbatical in England, 1930-31 (Box 1)
        - Moore correspondence with MED staff, 1932, 1933, summer 1934 (Box 1)
        - Meech correspondence with MED staff while in England, summer 1932 (Box 1)
        - Meech correspondence about dialect-survey documents 1932 (Box 1)
      - Mi-Mu (Box 1)
      - N (primarily Clark Northup) (Box 1)
      - O (Box 1)
      - P (Box 1)
      - Q-R (Box 1)
      - Sa-Sh (Box 1)
      - Si-Sy (Box 1)
      - Stevens, Brown & Co. (primarily with Meech) (Box 1)
      - T (Box 1)
      - Wa-We (Box 1)
      - Wh-Wi (Box 1)
      - Wo-Wy (Box 1)
      - X-Y-Z (Box 1)
    - Knott-Era Correspondence 1935-1945
      Knott's correspondence was with many of the same Middle English scholars as Moore's, as well as with others: Hope Emily Allen (a well known independent scholar who also worked for the EMED for a time), Baugh, Bryan, H.H. Carter (Indiana; about his dictionary of Middle English musical terms), Sir William Craigie (former editor of the OED, editor at the time of the Dictionary of American English at the University of Chicago and the Dictionary of the Older Scottish Tongue in Edinburgh), John S. Kenyon (Hiram College; primarily about their joint book, A Pronouncing Dictionary of American English, published in 1944), Kemp Malone (Johns Hopkins; also a member of the MLA's Advisory Committee), John M. Manly (Chicago), Savage, Kenneth Sisam (Oxford University Press), David Stevens (of the Rockefeller Foundation), J.S.P. Tatlock (California-Berkeley), and Clarence S. Yoakum (Dean of the University of Michigan Graduate School), as well as various volunteer readers. In addition to Knott, Fries, Meech, MED editor Harold Whitehall, and EMED editor Hereward Price answered letters.
      - A (Box 2)
      - Allen, Hope Emily (Box 2)
      - Ba-Bi (Box 2)
      - Bl-Br (Box 2)
      - Bu (Box 2)
      - Ca-Ch (Box 2)
      - Cl-Cu (Box 2)
      - D (Box 2)
      - E (Box 2)
      - F (Box 2)
      - G (Box 2)
      - Ha-He (Box 2)
      - Hi-Hy (Box 2)
      - I (Box 2)
      - International Filmbook Corp. (mainly with Fries) (Box 2)
      - J (Box 2)
      - Ka-Ke (Box 2)
      - Kenyon, John S. (mainly with Knott about their American Pronouncing Dictionary) (Box 2)
      - Ki-Ky (Box 2)
      - L (Box 2)
      - Leslie, John A. (inmate at Ohio Penitentiary) (Box 2)
      - Lewis, W.J. (printer in Oxford) (Box 2)
      - Long, Percy W. (Secretary, Modern Language Assn. of America) (Box 2)
      - Ma-Mc (Box 2)
      - Me (Box 2)
      - MED
        - Knott correspondence with MED staff before becoming editor, 1935-44 (Box 2)
        - Knott correspondence with MED staff while in England, summer 1939 (includes information about trip) (Box 2)
        - Knott correspondence while on sabbatical January-June 1942 (Box 2)
      - Merriam Co., G. & C. (Box 2)
      - Mi-Mu (Box 2)
      - N (Box 2)
      - O (Box 2)
      - Oxford University/Clarendon Presses (mainly with Kenneth Sisam) (Box 2)
      - P (Box 2)
      - Q (Box 2)
      - Ra-Ri (Box 3)
      - Ro-Ry (Box 3)
      - Sa-Sh (Box 3)
      - Si-Sy (Box 3)
      - Stevens, David (Rockefeller Foundation) (Box 3)
      - T (Box 3)
      - U (Box 3)
      - V (Box 3)
      - Wa-We (Box 3)
      - Wh-Wy (Box 3)
      - WPA (also NYA and FERA) (Box 3)
      - X-Y-Z (Box 3)
      - Yoakum, Clarence S. (Dean, Graduate School) (Box 3)
    - Administration and History
      From 1930 to 1939 the budgeting for the MED was combined with that for the EMED, with Moore and then Knott along with Fries for the EMED submitting joint budgets. Though money was tight in the early 1930s, Moore was mercifully spared from the financial problems that beset Knott. The project received grants during its early years (1931-1936) from the Rockefeller Foundation (through the ACLS), but that external support ended in February of 1936, and the University of Michigan had to assume the full cost of both projects. The financial limitations were partly responsible for the decisions first, in 1938, to suspend work on the MED and set the staffs of both the MED and the EMED to editing for the EMED and then, a year later, to resume work on the MED and postpone the EMED indefinitely. There is a full file on this subject, not to mention the official decisions themselves, which are in the MED Council files.
      - Budget and Salaries
        - 1930-1935 (Box 3)
        - 1935-1945 (Box 3)
      - Committee on Dictionaries Minutes
        - 1929-1938 (Box 3)
        - 1939-June 1945 (Box 3)
        - Louis Bredvold's copy 1929-1945 (Box 3)
      - Division of Work between MED and EMED, 1938-1939 (Box 3)
      - Mailing Lists of Various Kinds 1930-1945 (Box 3)
      - Meech, Sanford B.: Appointment and CV's 1930-1935 (Box 3)
      - Miscellaneous 1936, 1937 (Box 3)
      - OED Memorabilia (Box 3)
      - Reports
        - Annual (MED copy), 1930-1937 (Box 3)
        - Annual (MED Record), 1925-1934 (Box 3)
        - Annual (MED Record), 1935-1941 (Box 3)
        - Annual (reports not included in the preceding three files) 1932-1943 (Box 4)
        - Miscellaneous (primarily by Moore; Moore's notebook) 1930-1934 (Box 4)
        - Miscellaneous (on MED or including MED; printed), 1927-1941 (Box 4)
    - Editorial Matters
      - Bibliography
        - List of Writings to Be Quoted, 1933-34 (Box 4)
        - List of Short Titles A-Le 1940 (Box 4)
        - List of Short Titles Li-Z 1940 (Box 4)
      - Bodleian Library Manuscripts (Box 4)
      - Box Assignments and Editing (and Other) Progress (Box 4)
      - Dialects of Middle English (Moore) circa 1934 (Box 4)
      - Draft Entries and Quotations for B-Words (Box 4)
      - Materials Concerning Editing, Style, etc., 1937-45 (Box 4)
      - Miscellaneous (Box 4)
      - Papers by Knott on Editing the MED and Other Dictionaries, 1937-1942 (Box 4)
      - Printing of L-Sample
        - General 1937 (Box 4)
        - Completed Questionnaires 1937-1938 (Box 4)
      - Printing of A-Sample and Summary of Responses 1940-1944 (Box 4)
      - Science Editing (by Margaret Ogden) (Box 4)
      - Style Book 1936-1937 (Knott) (Box 4)
      - Style Book, Revised Edition 1939 (Knott) (Box 4)
      - Subentry List, with Powers' Vocabulary of Scientific Terms 1940 (Box 4)
    - Reading Program
      The reading program, which was of special importance during the Moore and Knott eras, has its own category (boxes 5 and 6; 2+ linear feet). It contains Moore's instructions for readers, lists of books to be read, extensive and detailed files on the texts analyzed, letters to readers and their replies, and inventories of the slips prepared at Cornell University and sent to the MED